A Finding Aid to the Carlen Galleries, Inc., Records, 1775-1997, bulk 1940-1986, in the Archives of American Art AAA.carlgall
Archives of American Art
- Loan (2002), 1775-1997; Series 4; (Reels 5746-5748)
  - Notebooks, 1928-1994; 4.4
    Five volumes of notebooks concerning Horace Pippin, Edward Hicks, and Robert Carlen. Three Horace Pippin notebooks contain correspondence with and about Pippin, photographs of Pippin and his works of art, exhibition catalogs and brochures, printed material, receipts, and cancelled checks. One notebook concerns Edward Hicks and contains correspondence about Hicks' paintings, photographs of his work, and printed matter. One notebook concerns Robert Carlen and contains photographs of Carlen, newsclippings, a small number of letters to Carlen, and a photocopy of Carlen's student record from the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts.
    Some of the Horace Pippin and Edward Hicks material in vols. 1-4 was microfilmed with Part 4 is partially duplicated in Part 2, but was significantly rearranged in the interim.
    - Vol. 1, Horace Pippin, 1940-1994 (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Vol. 2, Horace Pippin, 1942-1981 (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Vol. 3, Horace Pippin, 1994, n.d (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Vol. 4, Edward Hicks, 1944-1991 (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Vol. 5, Robert Carlen, 1975-1990 (Box NA, Reel 5748)
  - Printed Matter, 1944-1989; 4.5
    Newsclippings and miscellaneous printed material concerning various topics arranged in alphabetical order. The Artists, A-Z, File contains clippings and miscellaneous items about Anonymous, Joseph Boggs Beale, John George Brown, Thomas Eakins, Adolphus Ealey, Edward Hicks, Elizabeth Osborne, Horace Pippin, John Rodgers, Saint-Mémin, Elizabeth Sparhawk-Jones, and Grant Wood. The file on Collectors includes clippings about R. S. Ingersoll, Allen Funt, and Steven Straw.
    - Antiques, 1967-1989, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Art, Miscellaneous, 1974, 1989 (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Art Market, 1975-1981 (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Artists, A-Z, 1944-1989, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Big Sur Folk Festival (Nancy Carlen, Promoter), circa 1970s (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Carlen, Robert, 1941, 1964-1971 (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Carlen Galleries at Provident National Bank (exhibition checklists), 1973, 1976 (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Collectors, 1973-1980 (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Miscellaneous (not art related), undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - State Department, Diplomatic Reception Rooms, 1978-1978/79, 1980/81, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
  - Miscellaneous, 1775-1991; 4.6
    Prints found here include: Pickets by Lynd Ward; 3 Hand-Colored Prints in poor condition, including Currier and Ives George Washington's Reception by the Ladies on Passing on his Way to New York to be Inaugurated..., and 2 unidentified images.
    - Biographical, Health Insurance Card, 1954 (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Biographical, Medicare Card, Social Security Card, 1971, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Biographical, Inventory of Household Furnishings, 1980 (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Biographical, Inventory and Appraisal of the Estate of Robert Carlen, 1990-1991 (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Financial, Banking (deposit slips), 1958-1978 (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Financial, Taxes (tax returns), 1969 (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Notes, Business Notes, Lists, 1956, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Notes, Names, Addresses, Telephone Numbers, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Notes, Research Notes, 1775-1948, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Prints, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
  - Photographs, 1970; 4.7
    Photographs of antiques and artwork consist mainly of Carlen Galleries' stock and images retained for reference or comparative purposes. These undated photographs are categorized by medium and subject. Also included are photographs of people, and places. Photographs of miscellaneous subjects include photographs of a cover of an auction catalog for the sale of Peale's Museum Gallery of Oil Paintings, M. Thomas & Sons, Philadelphia, 1854; photograph of an inscription on the back of canvas, Bath Houses-Atlantic City Jas. Hamilton. 1868; and a model of a carriage. Also found is a folder of photographs of Wanamaker's Department Store in Philadelphia with a window display featuring selections from Carlen Galleries to advertise University Hospital Antiques Show; Carlen Galleries.
    - Antiques, Furniture, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Antiques, Metal Work, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Antiques, Miscellaneous, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Antiques, Porcelains, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Antiques, Rifle, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Artwork, Drawings, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Artwork, Needlework, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Artwork, Paintings, Biblical ( Peaceable Kingdom), undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Artwork, Paintings, Figures, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Artwork, Paintings, Genre, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Artwork, Paintings, History, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Artwork, Paintings, Landscape, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Artwork, Paintings, Marine, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Artwork, Paintings, Miscellaneous Subjects (animals, allegory), undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Artwork, Paintings, Native American, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Artwork, Paintings by Horace Pippin, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Artwork, Paintings, Portraits, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Artwork, Paintings, Still Life, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Artwork, Print, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Artwork, Sculpture, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Artwork, Wood Carvings, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - People, Robert Carlen and David Cohen (brother); Mrs. Jessie I. Bell (painter), 1970, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Places, Carlen Galleries (interior and exterior), undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Miscellaneous, Cover of Auction Catalog; Canvas Inscription; Model of Carriage, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)
    - Miscellaneous, Wanamaker's Department Store, Philadelphia, undated (Box NA, Reel 5748)